<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Winter-evenings communication with young novices in religion. Or Questions and answers about certaine chiefe grounds of Christian religion wherein every answer, rightly understood, hath the force of an oracle of God. By Iohn Carter, preacher of Gods Word.</title>
            <author>Carter, John, 1554-1635.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1628</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 46 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A18053</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 4696</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S116222</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99851439</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99851439</idno>
            <idno type="VID">16711</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A18053)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 16711)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1092:09)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Winter-evenings communication with young novices in religion. Or Questions and answers about certaine chiefe grounds of Christian religion wherein every answer, rightly understood, hath the force of an oracle of God. By Iohn Carter, preacher of Gods Word.</title>
                  <author>Carter, John, 1554-1635.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 38 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by the printers to the Vniversity of Cambridge, and are to be sold at London by R. Daniel at the Angel in Lumbard Street,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Cambridge] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1628.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catechisms, English.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:16711:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16711:1"/>
            <p>Winter-Evenings COMMVNICATION with Young Novices in RELIGION. OR Queſtions and Anſwers about certaine chiefe Grounds of Chriſtian RELIGION; wherein every Anſwer, rightly underſtood, hath the force of an Oracle of GOD.</p>
            <p>By IOHN CARTER, <hi>Preacher of Gods Word.</hi>
            </p>
            <bibl>IOHN 5. 39.</bibl>
            <q>Search the Scriptures.</q>
            <p>Printed by the Printers to the <hi>Vniver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of Cambridge,</hi> And are to be ſold at <hi>London</hi> by R. DANIEL <hi>at the Angel in Lumbard-Street.</hi> 1628.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:16711:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:16711:2"/>
            <head>Winter-Evenings COMMVNICATION with Young Novices in RELIGION.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the true Feare of God.</head>
               <p>QVESTION. <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>F what Religion are you?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwer.</hi> I feare the Lord, the God of heaven, who hath made the ſea, and the drie land, <hi>Ionah</hi> 1. 9.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>Many profeſſe as much as you doe, but who feare God in deed, and in truth?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> He that walketh in his uprightneſſe feareth the Lord, <hi>Prov.</hi> 14. 2.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is it to walk in uprightneſſe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To doe juſtly, and to love mercy, and
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:16711:3"/> to walk humbly with thy God, <hi>Mich.</hi> 6. 8.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>And who doe not feare the Lord, but despiſe him?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> He that is lewd in his waies, deſpiſeth him, <hi>Prov.</hi> 14. 2.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Who is lewd in his waies?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Whoſoever hateth to be reformed, and caſteth the words of God behinde him, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50. 17.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What reaſons have you to moove you to the effectuall ſtudy and practiſe of the true feare of God?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> God hath made all things for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, <hi>Prov</hi> 16. 4.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What other?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> In his hand is my breath, and all my waies, <hi>Dan.</hi> 5. 23.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What other?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> God is of purer eies then to behold iniquity, <hi>Habac.</hi> 1. 13.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What other reaſons have you?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> God will bring every worke to judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, with every ſecret thing, whether it be good or evill, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 12. 14.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:16711:3"/>
               <head>The Nature and Properties of <hi>GOD.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Queſtion. <hi>OF what nature or ſubſtance is the Lord?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> He is a Spirit, and muſt be wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhiped in ſpirit and in truth, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4. 24.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What manner of ſpirit is God?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> He is from everlaſting, to everlaſting; be filleth heaven and earth, <hi>Pſal. 90. 2. Ier.</hi> 23. 24.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What properties or vertues in God, are chiefly to be conſidered of us?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> That power belongeth unto God, and to thee O Lord mercy, that thou reward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt every man according to his workes, <hi>Pſal. 62. 11. 12. Exod.</hi> 34. 67.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. God is indeed moſt mighty, mercifull and juſt; What uſe is to be made thereof?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Be not afraid of them that kill the body, and after have no more that they can doe, <hi>Luk.</hi> 12. 4.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Whom then ſhall we feare?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Feare him which after he hath killed, hath power to caſt into hell, <hi>Luk.</hi> 12. 5.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What other uſe is to be made?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:16711:4"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To truſt in him at all times, to poure out our hearts before him, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 62. 8.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Creation.</head>
               <p>Queſtion. <hi>HOw did God make all things at the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Exceeding good, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. 31.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Whereof were all things made?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The worlds were framed by the word of God, ſo that things which are ſeen, were not made of things which doe appeare, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. 3.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How made he man?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> In his owne Image, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. 26.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Wherein ſtood that Image?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> In knowledge, righteouſneſſe, and true holineſſe, <hi>Col. 1. 10. Epheſ.</hi> 4. 24.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Whereof was the body of man framed?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Of the duſt of the ground, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2. 7.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What inſtruction ariſeth from thence?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Why is earth and aſhes proud? <hi>Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtic. 10. 9. Gen.</hi> 18. 25.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:16711:4"/>
               <head>The Providence of <hi>GOD.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Queſtion. <hi>VVHat have you learned concerning the divine Providence?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> God worketh all things after the counſell of his owne will, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1. 11.</p>
               <p>Q <hi>Worketh he ſo in the Church onely, and not in the reſt of the world?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Lord looketh downe from heaven, and beholdeth all the ſonnes of men, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 33. 13.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What manner of beholding is there ſpoken of?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> He faſhioneth their hearts every one, and conſidereth all their workes, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 33. 15.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>God is in all mens boſomes, and maketh their wretched inclinations and deviſes to ſerve his moſt holy ends: But doth this providence reach no further then the children of God, and the children of men?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A</hi> Yes; one Sparrow, whereof two are ſold for a farthing, ſhal not fall on the ground without your Father, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10. 29.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. And what ſaith the Lord yet further of thoſe ſparrows?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:16711:5"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Not one of them is forgotten before God, <hi>Luk.</hi> 12. 6.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What uſe is to be made hereof?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Even the very haires of your head are all numbred: Feare not, ye are of more value then many Sparrowes, <hi>Luk.</hi> 12. 7.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Feare not any want of proviſion or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection. But in a prosperous and wealthy estate, what uſe is to be made of it?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Beware leſt thine heart be lifted up, and thou forget the Lord thy God, ſaying, My power, and the might of mine hand hath gotten me this wealth, <hi>Deut.</hi> 8. 11. 14. 17.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is then to be remembred of us?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Thou ſhalt remember the Lord thy God: for it is he that giveth thee power to get wealth, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erſ.</hi> 18.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>But when we are under many and grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous temptations, and are much exerciſed with loſſes and croſſes, what uſe are we then to make hereof?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> I was dumb and opened not my mouth becauſe thou didſt it, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 39. 10.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What further uſe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Let them that ſuffer according to the will of God, commit the keeping of their ſoules to him, in well doing, as unto a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Creator, 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 4. 19.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:16711:5"/>
               <head>Of Sinne, and the bitter fruits of it.</head>
               <p>Queſtion. <hi>HAve our firſt parents</hi> Adam <hi>and</hi> Eve, <hi>with their poſterity, continued in their inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cencie?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> No; all have ſinned, and are deprived of the glory of God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. 23.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is ſinne?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The tranſgreſſion of Gods Law, 1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3. 4.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What was the firſt tranſgreſſion?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The eating of the tree whereof God commanded them that they ſhould not eate, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3. 11.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How were they brought to that?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Serpent beguiled <hi>Eve</hi> by his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilty, 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 3.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Who put that into the Serpent?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The old Serpent the Devill, who was a murtherer from the beginning, <hi>Revel. 12. 9. Ioh.</hi> 8. 44.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Was not he alſo made after Gods image at the firſt?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Yes; but he abode not in the truth, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 8. 44.</p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:16711:6"/>
               <p>Q. <hi>VVhat effect followed that fearefull fall of our firſt parents</hi> Adam <hi>and</hi> Eve?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> By ſinne death entred into the world, and paſſed upon all men, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. 12.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What death?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> They are dead in treſpaſſes and ſins, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2. 1, 2, 3.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>This is called ſpirituall death, depriving men of the favour, image, and life of God. Did not corporall death alſo follow?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Yes; Duſt thou art, ſaith the Lord, and to duſt ſhalt thou returne, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3. 19.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Is there not yet another death?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Yes; eternall death, to be caſt into hell, into the fire that never ſhall be quenched, <hi>Mark.</hi> 9. 45.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Doth not a naturall man, by living in ſinne, make his ſtate yet more grievous and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolerable?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> He treaſureth up to himſelfe wrath againſt the day of wrath, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2. 5.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>And is there no way or meanes left to man, whereby he may worke himſelfe out of this wofull plight, and recover his loſt dignity?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> No; What can a man give in exchange of his ſoule? <hi>Matth.</hi> 16. 26<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:16711:6"/>
               <head>Of the holy Goſpel, and of <hi>CHRIST IESVS.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Queſtion. <hi>SHall we then utterly deſpaire?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> God forbid; We have glad tidings from heaven, of great joy to all people, <hi>Luke</hi> 2. 10.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What tidings are thoſe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> That unto us is borne a Saviour, which is Chriſt the Lord, <hi>Luk.</hi> 2. 11.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. You have been taught, that by the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel is meant glad tydings, and here we have the ſumme of it. But who is this great Saviour? and how was he anointed to be the</hi> Chriſt, <hi>or</hi> Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſias, <hi>which words, as we know, ſignifie</hi> An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ointed?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> God anointed Ieſus of Nazareth with the holy Ghoſt, and with power, <hi>Act.</hi> 10. 38.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Why was he called</hi> Ieſus?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe he ſaveth his people from their ſinnes, as ſpake the Angel, <hi>Matth.</hi> 1. 21.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Of whom was he borne?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> eſpouſed to <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph</hi>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:16711:7"/> the ſonne of <hi>David, Matth.</hi> 1. 18, 20.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Why is David mentioned?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe he was to be made of his ſeed according to the fleſh, <hi>Rom. 1. 3. Matth.</hi> 1. 1.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>But how could a virgin conceive and beare a ſonne?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Holy Ghoſt came upon her, and the power of the higheſt did overſhadow her, <hi>Luk.</hi> 1. 35.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What came of that?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Therefore alſo that holy thing which was borne of her, was called the Sonne of God, <hi>Luk.</hi> 1. 35.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What other name was to be given him?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> They ſhall call his name <hi>Emmanuel, Matth. 1. 23. Eſa.</hi> 7. 14.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is that being interpreted?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> God with us, <hi>Matth.</hi> 1. 23.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What reaſon is there of that name?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> He is God manifeſted in the fleſh, 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 16.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What other reaſon is there of that name?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> God was in Chriſt, reconciling the world to himſelfe, not imputing their ſinnes unto them, 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 19.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:16711:7"/>
               <head>Redemption.</head>
               <p>Queſtion. <hi>HOw did God reconcile the world to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe by Chriſt?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> He made him to be ſinne for us, who knew no ſinne, 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 21.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. How did Chriſt become ſinne for us?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> He gave himſelfe for us an offering, and a ſacrifice of a ſweet ſmelling ſavour to God, <hi>Eph.</hi> 5. 2</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. When did he that?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> When he bare our ſinnes in his body on the tree, 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 24.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. Was the Sonne of God, the Lord of glory, hanged on the tree?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Yes; he humbled himſelf, and became obedient to the death, even the death of the croſſe, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2. 8.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. To what end did he undergoe all this hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> That we being delivered from ſinne, ſhould live in righteouſneſſe, 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2 24.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. Why ſuffered he that kinde of death, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then any other?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To declare that he was made a curſe for us, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. 13.</p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:16711:8"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. How doth that appeare?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is written, Curſed is every one that hangeth on tree, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. 13.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. Why was he made a curſe for us?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To redeeme us from the curſe of the Law, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. 13.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What is that curſe of the Law?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Curſed be he that continueth not in all the words of this Law to doe them, <hi>Deut. 27. 26. Gal.</hi> 3. 10.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Iuſtification.</head>
               <p>Queſtion. <hi>VVHo are they then that ſtand juſtified, or acquitted of all things from which they cannot be juſtified by the law of Moſes?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> By Ieſus Chriſt every one that belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth is juſtified, <hi>Act.</hi> 13. 39.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What is it to beleeve in Chriſt Ieſus?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To beleeve and know (with <hi>Peter</hi>) that he is the Chriſt, the Sonne of the living God, <hi>Iohn</hi> 6. 69.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What more?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> And that he hath loved me, and given himſelfe for me, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2. 20.</p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:16711:8"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. Wherein appeareth the excellencie and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of this faith?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> He that hath received his teſtimony, hath put to his ſeale, that God is true, <hi>Iohn</hi> 3. 33.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. And what the unbeleever?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> He maketh God a lyar, 1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5. 10.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. Why ſo?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe he beleeveth not the record that God witneſſeth of his Sonne, 1. <hi>Iohn</hi> 5. 11.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What is that record?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> That God hath given unto us eternall life, and this life is in his Sonne, 1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5. 11.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. Have workes of righteouſneſſe no place in our juſtification before God?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> No, for even <hi>Abraham</hi> our father be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeved God, and it was imputed to him for righteouſneſſe, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. 3.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. Why are workes excluded?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> That no fleſh ſhould glory in Gods preſence, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 29.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. Vpon what condition ſhall our faith be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to us for righteouſneſſe, as</hi> Abrahams <hi>was to him?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> If we beleeve in him that raiſed up Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus our Lord from the dead, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. 24.</p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:16711:9"/>
               <p>Q. <hi>Was Chriſt his raiſing from the dead a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of ſo great moment?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Yes; he was delivered for our offences, and raiſed againe for our juſtification, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. 25.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. Since he ſatisfied for our offences by his death, why is juſtification aſcribed to his reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> God raiſed him from the dead, and gave him glory, that our faith and hope might be in God, 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 21.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Can there be no faith nor hope in God, without Chriſt his raiſing up from the dead?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> No; if Chriſt be not raiſed up, our faith is vaine, we are yet in our ſinnes, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 17.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What obtaine we then at Gods hand by Chriſt his raiſing up from the dead?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The ſure mercies of David, <hi>Eſa. 55. 3. Act.</hi> 13. 34.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>VVhat are thoſe ſure mercies of David?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> God maketh an everlaſting covenant with us, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 55. 3. as he did with <hi>David.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What commeth to us by vertue of this everlaſting Covenant?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> We receive a kingdome which cannot be ſhaken or mooved, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12. 28.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>As</hi> David <hi>by promiſe received from God
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:16711:9"/> an everlaſting kingdome,</hi> 2. Sam. 7. 13. <hi>&amp;c. which promiſe was made good in and by the reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of Chriſt; ſo we: But where is this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of the kingdome, ſince they who moſt beleeve in him that raiſed up Ieſus our Lord from the dead, ſeeme many times of all other moſt miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, and that even to their very dying day?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> God, according to his abundant mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, hath begotten us againe unto a lively hope by the reſurrection of Ieſus Chriſt from the dead, 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 3.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What hope is that?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To an inheritance incorruptible and undefiled, and that fadeth not away, reſerved in heaven for us, 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 4.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>That is indeed reſerved for us: But how are we (ſo fraile by nature, and ſo beſet on every ſide with many ſore temptations) reſerved for it?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> We are kept (as in a fort) by the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of God, through faith unto ſalvation, 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 5.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>This ſalvation is to be revealed in the laſt time, as it is there ſaid: But how ſhall we poſſeſſe our ſoules in the meane ſeaſon?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> By our patience, <hi>Luk.</hi> 21. 19.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Is there ſo great need of patience?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Ye have need of patience, that after ye have done the will of God, ye might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:16711:10"/> the promiſe, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10. 36.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>It is true indeed. For we muſt needs drink of the cup which God reacheth unto us: neither can any be a true Chriſtian which doth not pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently offer himſelfe in ſacrifice to God.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Regeneration.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>HOw doe men attaine to that high dignity of being beleevers in Chriſt Ieſus?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> They are borne of God, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1. 13.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Muſt there then be a new birth?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> If any man be in Chriſt, he is a new creature, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 17.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. By what meanes are they borne of God?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> By the incorruptible ſeed of his word, 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 23.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What word of God is that?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The word which by the Goſpel is prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched unto them, 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 25.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What things are requiſite and neceſſary to the effectuall hearing of the Goſpel preached?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To have our hearts opened by God, to attend to it as <hi>Lydia, Act.</hi> 16. 14.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What elſe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To be taught and drawne of God, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 6. 44. 45.</p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:16711:10"/>
               <p>Q. <hi>What elſe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Beleeving to be ſealed with the holy Spirit of promiſe, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1. 13.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Sanctification. Mortification.</head>
               <p>Queſtion. <hi>VVE heard before how Chriſt bare our ſins in his body on the tree, that we being delivered from ſin, ſhould live in righteouſneſſe: What is it to live in righteouſneſſe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To live henceforth not after the luſts of men, but after the will of God, 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 4. 2.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the will of God?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> This is the will of God, even your Sanctification, 1. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4. 3.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>When is our ſanctification according to the will of God?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> When, as he that calleth us is holy, ſo we be holy in all manner of converſation, 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 15.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What reaſon is given why it ſhould be ſo?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe it is written, Be ye holy, for I am holy, <hi>Verſ.</hi> 16.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>So we are commanded to be perfect, as our Father which is in heaven is perfect; not for the degree, for in that we come infinitely ſhort of
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:16711:11"/> Gods holineſſe, or perfection; but for truth and univerſality of obedience to his lawes. This leaveth no liberty to men to live after the fleſh in any thing?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> No: For if you live after the fleſh, you ſhall die<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 13.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What courſe then is to be taken to ſave our lives?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> If through the Spirit we doe mortifie the deeds of the body, we ſhall live, <hi>Rom</hi> 8. 13.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>By this it plainly appeareth, that a neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity lieth upon us, of ſtriving to enter in at the ſtrait gate?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A</hi> Yes: Becauſe, Strait is the gate, and narrow is the way which leadeth unto life, and few there be that finde it, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7. 14.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the holy Scriptures.</head>
               <p>Queſtion. <hi>VVHence is the will of God to be learned?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Out of the holy Scriptures, all given by inſpiration of God, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 16.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>This is their excellency above all other writings, to be all given by inſpiration of God. Wherein elſe doe they excell all other writings?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> They are able to make us wiſe unto
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:16711:11"/> ſalvation, through faith which is in Chriſt Ieſus, 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3 15.</p>
               <p>Q <hi>How are we to be affected towards them, in regard of theſe excellencies?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Not to let them depart out of our mouth, but to meditate therein day and night, <hi>Ioſh.</hi> 1. 8.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>To what end?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> That we may obſerve and doe accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to all that is written therein, <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q What good will come of that?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Then ſhall we make our way proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, and then ſhall we have good ſucceſſe, <hi>Ioſh</hi> 1. 8.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. Doe not divers very ſtudious of the holy Scriptures meet with many loſſes and croſſes?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Yes; but marke the upright man, and behold the juſt, for the end of that man is peace, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37. 37.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. How commeth that to paſſe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Many are the troubles of the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, but the Lord delivereth him out of them all, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34. 19.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:16711:12"/>
               <head>Recovery and reconciliation after Offence.</head>
               <p>Queſtion. <hi>THe righteous are delivered at Gods appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed time, though no<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> alwaies corporally, yet moſt graciouſly and happily; their heavenly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther making all things to worke for their good, and ſending them, as he did his owne Sonne, and the holy Martyrs, by the chariot of the croſſe, into their heavenly countrey. But, when we fall into ſinne (as who liveth and ſinneth not?) what is then our refuge?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> We have an Advocate with the Father, <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> the righteous, and he is the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitiation for all our ſinnes, 1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 2. 1.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. Who maketh benefit hereof?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> He that confeſſeth and forſaketh his ſinne, ſhall have mercy, <hi>Prov. 28. 13. 1. Ioh. 1. 9. Pſal.</hi> 32. 6.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What is to be done then of every good man, when he hath offended God?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> For this ſhall every one that is godly make his praier unto God in a time when he may be found, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 32. 7.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What ſpeciall fruit commeth of that?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:16711:12"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Surely in the flood of great waters, they ſhall not come nigh unto him, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 32. 7.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. God will keep them from being ſwallowed up in the deepest gulfes of dangers, and even of death it ſelfe: Doth not this embolden men to ſinne, ſeeing their pardon is ſo ready and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> He that is borne of God keepeth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, that the wicked one toucheth him not, 1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5. 18.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. Satan toucheth him not with a mortall wound, but what courſe is to be taken in offences between man and man?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> If thy brother treſpaſſe againſt thee, rebuke him; and if he repent, forgive him, <hi>Luk</hi> 17. 3.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. How farre muſt this readineſſe to forgive extend?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> And if he treſpaſſe againſt thee ſeven times in a day, and ſeven times in a day turne againe to thee, ſaying, I repent, thou ſhalt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give him, <hi>Luk.</hi> 17. 4.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. And what is more to be done herein?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Confeſſe your faults one to another, and pray one for another that you may be healed, <hi>Iam.</hi> 5. 16.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:16711:13"/>
               <head>Good Workes.</head>
               <p>Queſtion. <hi>SInce we are ſaved by grace through faith,</hi> Epheſ. 2. 8. <hi>what ſuch need is there of good workes?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> They that have beleeved in God, muſt maintaine good workes for neceſſary uſes, <hi>Tit.</hi> 3. 8. 14.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What are thoſe neceſſary uſes?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> That men ſeeing our good workes, may glorifie our heavenly Father, <hi>Matth. 5. 16. 1. Pet.</hi> 2. 12.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What other?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> That we may adorne the doctrine of God our Saviour in all things, <hi>Tit.</hi> 2. 10.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What other?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Hereby the bowels of the Saints are refreſhed, <hi>Philem.</hi> 7.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What other?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> That we may make our calling and ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction ſure, 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 10.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. The foundation of God ſtandeth ſure, having the ſeale, The Lord knoweth them that are his; but the meaning is, to make it ſure to our owne ſoules and conſciences: What other neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:16711:13"/> uſe is there of good workes?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Our worke ſhall have a reward, 2. <hi>Chr. 15 7. Luk. 14. 14. Rev.</hi> 14. 13.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Even to a cup of cold water given to a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple in the name of a diſciple; but of grace, not of merit: What other neceſſary uſe is there?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> That if any obey not the word, they may without the word be won by our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation, 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. 1. 2.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Be won to the love and admiration of the word, and ſo be prepared to their converſion. Is there any other uſe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> So is the will of God, that by well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doing we may put to ſilence the ignorance of fooliſh men, 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 15.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What ſpeciall motive is there to ſtirre us up unto forwardneſſe and fervency in the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of good workes?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Chriſt gave himſelfe for us, that he might redeem us from all iniquity, <hi>Tit.</hi> 2. 14.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>And what more?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> And purifie to himſelfe a peculiar people, zealous of good workes, <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What is the danger of not being zealous of good workes?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> If we be luke-warme, and neither cold nor hot, the Lord will ſpew us out of his mouth, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3. 16.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:16711:14"/>
               <head>Of the Law, or ten Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements.</head>
               <p>Queſtion. <hi>IN the performance of good workes, what guid are we to follow? Will not the light of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, the precepts and examples of men account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed wiſe, civill, and honeſt, ſerve the turne?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> What is written in the Law, ſaith Chriſt, how readeſt thou? <hi>Luk.</hi> 10. 26.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>So indeed he anſwered a Lawyer, who would needs know of him what he ſhould doe. And againe,</hi> Mat. 19. 17. <hi>to a young man enquiring of him, what good thing he ſhould doe, his anſwer was, Keep the Commandements. Teaching us plainely, that a good worke, is ſome good thing, done in obedience to the Law, or Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: Which are thoſe Commandements?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The ten Commandements which the Lord ſpake in the mount, out of the mids of the fire, <hi>Deut.</hi> 10. 4.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Why out of the mids of the fire, and with thunders and lightnings, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> That his feare may be before us that we ſinne not, <hi>Exod.</hi> 20. 20.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How came they to be written?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:16711:14"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Lord delivered them to <hi>Moſes</hi> in two tables of ſtone, written with his owne finger, <hi>Deut.</hi> 9 10.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>They were written by the immediate pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of God: What is the ſumme of the firſt Table, or foure firſt Commandements?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Lord our God is one Lord; and, Thou ſhalt love the Lord thy God with all thine heart, and with all thy ſoule, and with all thy minde, and with all thy ſtrength, <hi>Mar.</hi> 12. 29. 30.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the ſumme of the ſecond Table, or ſix laſt Commandements?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Thou ſhalt love thy neighbour as thy ſelfe, <hi>Mark.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 31.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. Give me in like manner the ſhort ſumme of every ſeverall Commandement; What is it of the first, Thou ſhalt have none other Gods be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mee?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Know God, ſerve him with a perfect heart and willing minde, cleave to him, 1. <hi>Chron. 28. 9. Deut.</hi> 10. 20.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. And they that know thy Name will truſt in thee, ſaith</hi> David, <hi>Pſal. 9. 10. What of the ſecond, Thou ſhalt not make to thy ſelfe any gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven image?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> In Divine worſhip, obſerve to doe whatſoever God commandeth, adde nothing
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:16711:15"/> there-to, nor diminiſh ought there-from, <hi>Deut.</hi> 12. 30. 31. 32.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What of the third, Thou ſhalt not take the Name of the Lord? &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Thou ſhalt ſweare the Lord liveth in truth, in judgement, and in righteouſneſſe, and (every way elſe) knowing God, glorifie him as God, <hi>Ier. 4. 2. Rom.</hi> 1. 21.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What of the fourth, Remember the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath, to keep it holy?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Conſecrate the Sabbath as glorious to the Lord, and honour him, not doing thine owne waies, nor ſeeking thine owne pleaſure, nor ſpeaking thine own words, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 58. 13.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What of the fifth, Honour thy father and thy mother?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Render to all their dues, giving honour to every one, as the Lord hath diſtributed to them, as the Lord hath called, <hi>Rom. 13. 7. 1. Cor.</hi> 7. 17.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Render to all their dues; both to ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours, as parents, magiſtrates, miniſters, aged, &amp;c. and to inferiours, according to their rank, and the truſt and charge committed to us. What of the ſixth Commandement, Thou ſhalt not kill.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Put on the bowels of mercy, kinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe humbleneſſe of minde, meekneſſe, long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuffering, forbearing and forgiving one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>Col.</hi> 3. 12.</p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:16711:15"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What of the ſeventh Commandement, Thou ſhalt not commit adultery?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Poſſeſſe thy veſſell in holineſſe and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and not in luſts of concupiſcence, 1. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4. 4.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What of the eighth, Thou ſhalt not ſteale?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Let no man goe beyond, or defraud his brother in any matter, for God is an avenger of all ſuch, 1. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4. 6.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What of the ninth, Thou ſhalt not beare falſe witneſſe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Speake the truth in or from the heart, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 15. 2.</p>
               <p>Q <hi>What of the tenth, Thou ſhalt not covet?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> In whatſoever ſtate thou art, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with be thou content, <hi>Phil.</hi> 4. 11.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Can you fulfill all theſe commandements?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> No; In many things we offend all, <hi>Iam.</hi> 3. 2.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Why can you not fulfill them?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe the Law is ſpirituall, and I am carnall, ſold under ſinne, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7. 14.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What uſe is there then of the Law?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> By the Law is the knowledge of ſin, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. 20.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>To what end?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> That it might be our School-maſter, to bring us to Chriſt, that we might be juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:16711:16"/> by faith, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. 24.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>When the Law hath humbled us, and brought us to Chriſt, what uſe hath it then?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To be a lampe unto our feet, and a light unto our paths. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. 105.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Praier.</head>
               <p>Queſtion. <hi>BEſides the continuall exerciſe of the holy Scriptures, and practiſe of good workes, what ſpeciall meanes have we to uphold our weak faith, and to enflame our cold hearts unto more fervent charity and zeale?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Aske and it ſhall be given you, ſeek and ye ſhall finde, knock and it ſhall be open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto you, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7. 7.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What encouragement have we thereunto?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A</hi> For every one that asketh receiveth, and he that ſeeketh, &amp;c. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 8.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. Not onely the Apostles and the Saints that excell in vertue, but every penitent petitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, none excepted: What other encouragment have we?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Parents that are evill give good gifts unto their children, how much more ſhall our heavenly Father give good gifts, yea, even the holy Ghoſt, to us that deſire him? <hi>Mat. 7. 11. Luk.</hi> 11. 13.</p>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:16711:16"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. How is praier limited?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> If we aske any thing according to his will, he heareth us, 1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5. 14.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. In whoſe name or mediation are we to aske?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Whatſoever you ſhall aske the Father in my Name, ſaith Chriſt, he will give it you, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 16. 23.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What things are abſolutely neceſſary in praier to make it avaleable?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To abide in Chriſt, and to have his words abiding in us, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 15. 7.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What elſe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To aske in faith and waver not, <hi>Iam.</hi> 1. 6.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What elſe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To forgive if any offence be, or elſe our heavenly Father will not forgive us, <hi>Mark.</hi> 11. 25. 26.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What elſe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To be moſt humble with the poore Publicane, leſt we take the repulſe with the proud Phariſee, <hi>Luk.</hi> 18. 9.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What elſe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To be fervent in praier, and not faint, <hi>Iam. 5. 16. Luk.</hi> 18. 1.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What ſay you of thankeſgiving to God?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Pray continually: In all things give thankes, 1. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5. 17, 18.</p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:16711:17"/>
               <p>Q. <hi>In all things ſmall or great, proſperous, or adverſe: But what reaſon is there for that?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> This is the will of God in Chriſt Ieſus towards you, 1. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5. 18.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What other reaſon is there?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> He that offereth praiſe ſhall glorifie me, ſaith the Lord, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50. 23.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. VVhat ſet forme of praier hath Chriſt left unto us, to pray, and to frame our praiers by?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> After this manner pray ye; or when you pray, ſay, <hi>Our Father which art in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, &amp;c. Matth. 6. 9. Luk.</hi> 11. 2.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. Of this moſt holy praier I have briefly ſet downe my minde elſe where?</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Sacraments.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>ARe not Baptiſme and the Lords Supper worthy meanes alſo to uphold our weake faith, and to further our zeale towards God, and charity one towards another?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Yes; For theſe Sacraments are ſeales of the righteouſneſſe of faith, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. 11.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. They are indeed ſeales for confirmation of our moſt holy faith, which even our father</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham <hi>himſelfe had need of: But are they not
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:16711:17"/> in like manner ſeales for confirmation of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an unity and amity?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Yes; By one Spirit we are all baptiſed into one body, and have been all made to drinke into one ſpirit, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. 13.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. This is a marvellous myſtery, by one ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit to be all incorporate in our Baptiſme, into me myſticall body of Chriſt, which is his holy Catholick Church; and to be all made to drinke in the Lords Supper into one Spirit, by partaking the myſticall Cup, or quickning blood of Chriſt Ieſus, truely exhibited to all the faithfull therein. What doth this bleſſed <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion and Communion with our Head Chriſt, and with his holy Body the Church, neceſſarily binde us unto?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To an endeavour of keeping the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Spirit in the bond of peace, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4. 3.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. When is that bond of peace kept unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> When there be no diſſentions among us, but we be knit together in one minde, and in one judgement, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 10.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What is Baptiſme?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The waſhing of the new birth, <hi>Tit.</hi> 3. 5.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. Wherein conſiſteth this waſhing of the new birth?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Not in putting away the filth of the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:16711:18"/> fleſh; but in the renewing of the holy Ghoſt 1. <hi>Pet. 3. 21. Tit.</hi> 3. 5.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What is the manner and meanes of this renewing of us, who are ſo wholly polluted and uncleane by nature?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> We are waſhed, we are ſanctified, we are juſtified, in the Name of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, and by the Spirit of God, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 11.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>We are waſhed in Baptiſme, in token that we are ſanctified and juſtified by the merit of Chriſt, in whoſe Name we are baptiſed, and by the efficacie of Gods Spirit given unto us there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in: But why are we baptiſed in the Name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the holy Ghoſt?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> In token of the Covenant betwixt God the Father, Sonne, and holy Ghoſt, and us, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. 11.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>As Circumciſion was, ſo Baptiſme is a ſigne of the Covenant between God and his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: What is that Covenant on Gods part?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> That he will be our God, and the God of our ſeed, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. 11.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What on our part?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> We paſſe into the Covenant of God, to be his people, and ſo to obſerve all things, whatſoever Chriſt hath commanded us; <hi>Deut. 29. 12. Mat.</hi> 28. 20.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Is not this to make three Gods?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:16711:18"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> No; Theſe three, the Father, the Word, and the holy Ghoſt are one, 1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5. 7.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>They are one in ſubſtance and conſent, yet three Perſons, or diſtinct manners of being in the Godhead: What is proper to the perſon of the Father?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To be called one God, and the onely true God, of whom are all things, 1. <hi>Cor. 8. 6. Ioh.</hi> 17. 3.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>The Godhead is commonly aſcribed to the Father, becauſe in him is the beginning of it: who hath not onely his eſſence as God, but his perſonall being as Father of himſelfe: he is alſo called the onely true God, not to exclude the Sonne, and the holy Ghoſt (who are of the ſame ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance and glory with him) but all idols and creatures onely: What is proper to the perſon of the Sonne?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> He is the onely begotten of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the power of God, and the wiſdome of God, by whom are all things, <hi>Ioh. 1. 14. 1. Cor.</hi> 1. 24. and 8. 6.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is proper to the perſon of the holy Ghoſt?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> He proceedeth and is ſent of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and the Sonne, from whom he worketh all, in all things, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 14. 26. and 15. 26. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. 11.</p>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:16711:19"/>
               <p>Q. <hi>Set downe ſome few texts of holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, prooving this moſt high and incomprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible myſterie, the Trinity in Vnity, and the Vnity in Trinity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Matth.</hi> 3. 16. 17. and 28. 19. 1. <hi>Cor. 13. 13. Epheſ. 2. 18. 1. Ioh. 5. 7. Revel.</hi> 1. 4. 5. Let him that readeth underſtand, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the Lords Supper?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Communion of the Body and Blood of Chriſt, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 16.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the bread which is ſolemnely bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and broken?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The body of Chriſt broken for us, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 24.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. And what is the Cup of bleſſing which we bleſſe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The blood of Chriſt, or the New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament in his blood, <hi>Matth. 26. 28. 1. Cor.</hi> 11. 25.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. Doth not this make for Popiſh tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Nothing at all: It is the Spirit that quickeneth, the fleſh profiteh nothing, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 6. 63.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. It is moſt true, that the ſpirit, or ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall receiving of the fleſh and blood of Chriſt crucified for us, by faith in him, giveth life to the receiver: the fleſh, or bodily receiving with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:16711:19"/> that, profiteth nothing: But why are we to eate this Bread, and drinke this Cup?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Doe this in remembrance of me, ſaith our bleſſed Saviour twice over, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 24. 25.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>To what end are we ſo ſolemnely to be put in remembrance of him in this holy action?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> That ſo often as we eate this bread and drink this cup, we may ſhew the Lords death till he come, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 26.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>His moſt bitter and meritorious death, with the ſweet fruits of it, are upon this occaſion to be declared at all hands, both publickly, and privately, with the greateſt alacrity, joy, thanke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe, and zeal, that poſſibly can be: But how are we to prepare and addreſſe our ſelves to this holy banquet?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Let every man examine himſelfe, and ſo let him eat of this bread, and drinke of this cup, 1. <hi>Cor</hi> 11. 28.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What is the danger of the neglect hereof?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To be guilty of the body and blood of Chriſt, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 27.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>No marvell, ſince abuſe offered to the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, which is an holy inſtrument, ſeale, and image of the King of Kings, even by divine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, muſt needs redound to the Lord him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe: They muſt needs therefore eat and drinke
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:16711:20"/> their owne damnation, that doe ſo requite the Lord for this ineſtimable mercy: But whereof muſt we chiefly examine our ſelves?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Whether we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> in the faith; whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Chriſt be in us or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p>Q <hi>Whereby will it appeare that we be of ſound religion, and have ſaving faith?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Saving faith purifieth the heart, <hi>Act.</hi> 15. 9.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How elſe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It worketh alſo by charity, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. 6.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. How elſe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It maketh us as new borne babes, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire the ſincere milke of the Word, that we may grow thereby, 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 2.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Whereby ſhall we know that Chriſt is in us?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Hereby we know that Chriſt abideth in us, even by the Spirit that he hath given un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us, 1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3. 24</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. And how may the Spirit of God be diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in us?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> By his fruits; Love, joy, peace, long-ſuffering, gentleneſſe, goodneſſe, faith, meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, temperance. <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. 22, 23.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How may we be aſſured, that the fruits of the Spirit are in us in truth?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> If we live in the Spirit, let us walke in the Spirit, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. 25.</p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:16711:20"/>
               <p>Q <hi>When, by living and walking in the Spirit, that is, by the habite or cuſtomary practiſe of his fruits, with a holy delight therein, we have found that Chriſt abideth in us: What remaineth further to be examined?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> How we grow in grace, and in the knowledge of our Lord and Saviour Ieſus Chriſt, 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 18.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>A very neceſſary point to be examined of us all; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,: Chriſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> not to grow, is to goe downe the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>: But when is this our ſolemne and ſerious examination of our ſelves throughly performed?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> When having conſidered our waies, we turne our feet unto Gods teſtimonies, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. 59.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>Queſtion. <hi>VVHat is conſtantly to be done of him that deſireth a quiet life, and to ſee good daies in this world?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Keep thy tongue from evill, and thy lips from ſpeaking guile: Depart from evill and doe good, ſeek peace and purſue it, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34. 13. 14.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. And what is to be done to eſcape the moſt deſperate dangers that can befall men here, or hereafter?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:16711:21"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Watch you, ſaith Chriſt, and pray continually, that you may be accounted wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to eſcape all theſe things, that ſhall come to paſſe, and to ſtand be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Sonne of man, <hi>Luk.</hi> 21. 36.</p>
               <epigraph>
                  <bibl>ACTS 24.</bibl>
                  <q>
                     <p>15. <hi>I have hope towards God, that there ſhall be a reſurrection of the dead, both of the juſt, and unjuſt.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>16. <hi>And herein I exerciſe my ſelfe, to have alwaies a conſcience void of offence, toward God, and toward men.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:16711:21"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
